Devotees understand, you get the ... And by observing the pastimes of Mahāprabhu ...
A bhakták értik, hogy... Mahāprabhu kedvteléseinek a megfigyelésével...
Mahāprabhu's pastimes put all the emphasis upon Prabhu-priya,
Mahāprabhu kedvtelései minden hangsúlyt a Prabhu-priyára helyeznek,
the one of who is most dear to Kṛṣṇa.
arra, aki a leges-legkedvesebb Kṛṣṇa számára.
[Krishna As Krishna Das]
[Kṛṣṇa mint Kṛṣṇa Dās]
yadi gaura nā hoito, tabe ki hoito, kemone dharitām de
yadi gaura nā hoito, tabe ki hoito, kemone dharitām de
rādhār mahimā, prema-rasa-sīmā, jagate jānāto ke
rādhār mahimā, prema-rasa-sīmā, jagate jānāto ke
In fact here Vāsudev Ghoṣ is saying, “This is why Mahāprabhu came down.”
Valójában itt Vāsudeva Ghoṣ azt mondja: "Ez az, amiért Mahāprabhu alászállt."
Someone will say, “Well, I thought He came to give Kṛṣṇa-prema.”
"Nos, azt hittem, azért jött, hogy Kṛṣṇa-premát adjon."
“Well, where does Kṛṣṇa-prema come from?”
"Nos, honnan is jön a Kṛṣṇa-prema?"
They’ll say, “Oh, from Kṛṣṇa.”
Erre azt mondják, 'Ó, Kṛṣṇától."
Yeah, but who ... Kṛṣṇa is not the receptacle of Kṛṣṇa-prema.
Igen, de... nem Kṛṣṇa biztosítja a Kṛṣṇa-premát.
He is the object of Kṛṣṇa-prem.
Ő a Kṛṣṇa-prema tárgya.
He is not the one possessing the prema for Kṛṣṇa
Ő nem az, aki birtokolja a Kṛṣṇa-premát,
until He embraces the position of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
addig, amíg magára nem ölti Śrīmati Rādhārāṇī pozícióját.
And once experiencing that, then He wants to share that with everyone.
És amint megtapasztalja, Ő mindenkivel meg is akarja osztani.
So it’s saying, rādhāra mahimā— He descended
Vagyis ez a rādhā mahimā — alászállt,
to broadcast the glories of Rādhārāṇī in the world.
hogy közvetítse Rādhārāṇī dicsőségét a világon.
And prema-rasa-sīmā— the limits of Kṛṣṇa-prema.
És prem-rasa-sīmā — a Kṛṣṇa-prema legfelső határait.
That’s why Mahāprabhu has descended.
Ezért szállt alá Mahāprabhu.
sva-bhaktebhyaḥ śuddhāḿ nija-bhajana-mudrām upadiśan [Cc: Ādi-līlā, 3.66]
sva-bhaktebhyaḥ śuddhāḿ nija-bhajana-mudrām upadiśan [Cc: Ādi-līlā 3.66]
Rūpa Goswāmī says in the “Chaitanyāṣṭakam”,
Rūpa Gosvāmī mondja a "Caitanyāṣṭakam"-ban,
sadopāsyaḥ śrīmān dhṛta-manuja-kāyaiḥ praṇayitāṁ
sadopāsyaḥ śrīmān dhṛta-manuja-kāyaiḥ praṇayitāṁ
vahadbhir gīr-vāṇair giriśa-parameṣṭhi-prabhṛtibhiḥ [Cc: Ādi-līlā, 3.66]
vahadbhir gīr-vāṇair giriśa-parameṣṭhi-prabhṛtibhiḥ [Cc: Ādi-līlā, 3.66]
This is so extraordinary [that] Brahmā and Śiva are disguised as human beings,
Ez igazán rendkívüli, hogy Brahma és Śiva embernek álcázzák magukat,
as are other gods and goddesses, to come and have a glimpse
ahogy más istenségek és istennők is, hogy eljöjjenek és megpillantsák,
of how beautiful Kṛṣṇa looks when He is under the influence of the heart and halo of Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī—
milyen gyönyörű Kṛṣṇa, amikor Śrīmati Rādhārāṇī szívének és dicsőségének hatalma alatt áll —
when Kṛṣṇa’s been converted into a devotee.
amikor Kṛṣṇa átalakul bhaktává.
As Guru Mahārāj identifies the concept of Gaura Gadādhar
Ahogyan Guru Mahārāja azonosította Gaura-Gadādhara koncepcióját
as the āchārya-līlā of Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa.
Rādhā és Kṛṣṇa ācārya-lilájával.
But still the point is there
De a lényegi pont az,
that Kṛṣṇa, as He’s become a devotee
ahogyan Kṛṣṇa bhaktává változik,
and celebrating devotion,
és az odaadást ünnepli,
so Her servitors, they always want to promote Her.
eközben Rādhārāṇī szolgálói mindig Rādhārāṇīt akarják támogatni.
She, being of a particular nature, is always trying to promote Her servitors
Rādhārāṇī pedig, az ő sajátos természete szerint próbál kedvezni a szolgálóinak,
to bring them in closer connection with Kṛṣṇa.
hogy elősegítse a közvetlen kapcsolatot Kṛṣṇával.
But they know, as the name indicated by Śrīla Saraswatī Ṭhākur,
De tudják, ahogy a Śrīla Sarasvatī Ṭhākur által jelzett név mutatja,
Śrī Vārṣhabhānavi Devī Dayita,
Śrī Vārṣhabhānavi Devī Dayita,
[one] who’s so dear to Vārṣhabhānavi Devī, means Śrīmatī Rādhārāṇī.
az, aki oly kedves Vārṣhabhānavi Devī-nek, azaz Śrīmati Rādhārāṇī-nak.
They’re always, they’re exclusively promoting Her.
Ők mindig és kizárólagosan Őt [Rādhārāṇī] akarják szolgálni.
And not out of some just sense of obligation or loyalty,
És nem csak a valamiféle kötelezettség vagy a hűség miatt,
you could say, underneath it all there is a strategy too,
hanem a háttérben mégis van egy elképzelés,
identified by Śrīla Guru Mahārāj as
ahogy azt Śrīla Guru Mahārāja kifejezte,
the incomparable quality of Kṛṣṇa conception
hogy a Kṛṣṇa-tudat összehasonlíthatatlan minősége
and connection that comes through Her,
és a Rajta [Rādhārāṇī] keresztül létrejövő kapcsolat,
it’s incomparable.
az egyedülálló.
Mahābhāva-svarūpiṇī Rādhā Ṭhākurāṇī.
Mahābhāva-svarūpiṇī Rādhā Ṭhākurāṇī.